A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Council of State, 1776-1861
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Council of State, 1776-1861
The Library of Virginia
35356, 50867
8.6 cu. ft. (69 boxes/86 volumes)
Virginia. Council of State.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Use the microfilm (Misc. reels 2981-2998) instead of the original journals.
Acquisition Information
Transferred prior to 1905 [Acc. 35356 and Acc. 50867].
Alternative Form Available
Restricted access: use microfilm [Miscellaneous Reels 2981-2998] for the Journals. The minutes have not been microfilmed.
Biographical Information
The Council of State was established by the constitution adopted on June 29, 1776, to assist the governor in the administration of the government. It had its origin in the earlier Council of colonial Virginia, but was a more powerful check on the authority of the governor. The council members were elected by the General Assembly rather than appointed by the governor as had been the case with the colonial Council. By the middle of the nineteenth century, however, the need for a stronger chief executive had become evident. The new constitution adopted in 1851 made no provision for an advisory council, and on January 15, 1852, the Council of state adjourned for the last time.
Scope and Content
Records, 1776-1861, including journals and minute books of the Virginia Council of State.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Journals, 1776-1852 [Acc. 35356]; and
Series II: Minutes, 1776-1852, 1861 [Acc. 50867].
Contents List
- Series I: Journals, 1776-1852 [Acc. 35356]., Extent: 6.2 cu. ft. (59 boxes/62 volumes). (Box 1-59)
  - Journal, 1776 July 12-1777 May 30 [Misc. reel 2981] (Box 1)
  - Journal, 1777 June -1778 December 31 [Misc. reel 2981] (Volume v. 1)
  - Journal, 1781 January 1-November 30 [Misc. reel 2982] (Box 2)
  - Journal, 1781 December 1-1782 November 15 [Misc. reel 2982] (Box 3)
  - Journal, 1782 November 18-1783 October 30 [Misc. reel 2982] (Box 4)
  - Journal, 1783 November 3-1785 December 29 [Misc. reel 2983] (Box 5)
  - Journal, 1786 January 2-1787 August 28 [Misc. reel 2983] (Box 6)
  - Journal, 1787 March 20-1792 October 4 [Misc. reel 2985] (Box 7)
    Note the reel number [out of order].
  - Journal, 1787 October 1-1789 March 28 [Misc. reel 2984] (Box 8)
  - Journal, 1789 April 1-1791 October 15 [Misc. reel 2984] (Box 9)
  - Journal, 1791 October 17-1793 October 31 [Misc. reel 2986] (Box 10)
  - Journal, 1793 November 2-1795 June 30 [Misc. reel 2986] (Box 11)
  - Journal, 1795 July 2-1797 April 27 [Misc. reel 2986] (Box 12)
  - Journal, 1797 May 4-1798 October 30 [Misc. reel 2987] (Box 13)
  - Journal, 1798 November 1-1799 October 29 [Misc. reel 2987] (Box 13)
  - Journal, 1799 November 1-1801 February 7 [Misc. reel 2987] (Box 14)
  - Journal, 1801 February 14-1803 July 9 [Misc. reel 2987] (Box 15)
  - Journal, 1803 July 23-1806 December 1 [Misc. reel 2988] (Box 16)
  - Journal, 1806 December 7-1808 December 1 [Misc. reel 2988] (Box 17)
  - Journal, 1808 December 5-1809 December 11 [Misc. reel 2989] (Box 18)
  - Journal, 1809 December 12-1810 December 7 [Misc. reel 2989] (Box 19)
  - Journal, 1810 December 10-1811 December 5 [Misc. reel 2989] (Box 20)
  - Journal, 1811 December 6-1812 December 2 [Misc. reel 2989] (Box 21)
  - Journal, 1812 December 3-1813 December 4 [Misc. reel 2990] (Box 22)
  - Journal, 1813 December 9-1814 October 12 [Misc. reel 2990] (Box 23)
  - Journal, 1814 October 13-1815 December 8 [Misc. reel 2990] (Box 24)
  - Journal, 1815 December 9-1816 November 9 [Misc. reel 2991] (Box 25)
  - Journal, 1816 November 12-1817 December 8 [Misc. reel 2991] (Box 26)
  - Journal, 1817 December 9-1818 December 16 [Misc. reel 2991] (Box 26)
  - Journal, 1818 December 17-1819 December 14 [Misc. reel 2992] (Box 27)
  - Journal, 1819 December 14-1820 December 7 [Misc. reel 2992] (Box 28)
  - Journal, 1820 December 19-1821 December 6 [Misc. reel 2992] (Box 29)
  - Journal, 1821 December 7-1822 December 9 [Misc. reel 2992] (Box 30)
  - Journal, 1822 December 19-1823 December 9 [Misc. reel 2992] (Box 31)
  - Journal, 1823 December 12-1824 December 10 [Misc. reel 2993] (Box 32)
  - Journal, 1824 December 14-1825 December 9 [Misc. reel 2993] (Box 33)
  - Journal, 1825 December 13-1826 December 8 [Misc. reel 2993] (Box 34)
  - Journal, 1826 December 12-1827 December 8 [Misc. reel 2993] (Box 35)
  - Journal, 1827 December 13-1828 December 9 [Misc. reel 2993] (Box 36)
  - Journal, 1828 December 12-1829 December 16 [Misc. reel 2994] (Box 37)
  - Journal, 1829 December 22-1831 March 30 [Misc. reel 2994] (Box 38)
  - Journal, 1831 March 31-1832 March 11 [Misc. reel 2994] (Box 39)
  - Journal, 1832 April 3-1833 March 30 [Misc. reel 2994] (Box 40)
  - Journal, 1833 April 2-1834 March 29 [Misc. reel 2995] (Box 41)
  - Journal, 1834 March 31-1835 March 28 [Misc. reel 2995] (Box 42)
  - Journal, 1835 April 1-1836 March 30 [Misc. reel 2995] (Box 43)
  - Journal, 1836 March 31-1837 March 30 [Misc. reel 2995] (Box 44)
  - Journal, 1837 March 31-1838 March 30 [Misc. reel 2995] (Box 45)
  - Journal, 1838 March 31-1839 March 29 [Misc. reel 2996] (Box 46)
  - Journal, 1839 April 1-1840 March 30 [Misc. reel 2996] (Box 47)
  - Journal, 1840 April 1-1841 March 30 [Misc. reel 2996] (Box 48)
  - Journal, 1841 March 31-1842 March 30 [Misc. reel 2996] (Box 49)
  - Journal, 1842 March 31-1843 March 30 [Misc. reel 2996] (Box 50)
  - Journal, 1843 April 1-1844 March 30 [Misc. reel 2997] (Box 51)
  - Journal, 1844 April 1-1845 March 29 [Misc. reel 2997] (Box 52)
  - Journal, 1845 March 31-1846 March 30 [Misc. reel 2997] (Box 53)
  - Journal, 1846 March 31-1847 March 30 [Misc. reel 2997] (Box 54)
  - Journal, 1847 March 31-1848 March 30 [Misc. reel 2997] (Box 55)
  - Journal, 1848 March 31-1849 March 29 [Misc. reel 2998] (Box 56)
  - Journal, 1849 March 31-1850 March 29 [Misc. reel 2998] (Box 57)
  - Journal, 1850 April 1-1851 March 29 [Misc. reel 2998] (Box 58)
  - Journal, 1851 March 31-1852 Jan. 15 [Misc. reel 2998] (Box 59)
- Series I: Minute books, 1776-1852, 1861 [Acc. 50867]., Extent: 2.4 cu. ft. (9 boxes/24 volumes). (Box 60-68)
  - Minute books, 1776 October 3-1777 March 1 (Box 60)
  - Minute books, 1779 March 22-1780 July 8 (Box 60)
  - Minute books, 1781 January 1-1782 August 31 (Box 61)
  - Minute books, 1785 February 10-1786 January 16 (Box 61)
  - Minute books, 1787 December 5-1788 October 2 (Box 62)
  - Minute books, 1793 December 2-1794 October 4 (Box 62)
  - Minute books, 1797 May 25-1798 January 25 (Box 62)
  - Minute books, 1800 July 5-December 31 (Box 62)
  - Minute books, 1806 June 6-1807 January 22 (Box 62)
  - Minute books, 1810 February 24-1811 June 22 (Box 62)
  - Minute books, 1816 November 9-1818 June 29 (Box 63)
  - Minute books, 1820 April 22-1822 January 18 (Box 63)
  - Minute books, 1822 January 22-1823 September 2 (Box 64)
  - Minute books, 1823 September 5-1825 March 11 (Box 64)
  - Minute books, 1825 March 15-1827 April 21 (Box 65)
  - Minute books, 1827 April 24-1830 June 10 (Box 65)
  - Minute books, 1830 June 11-1832 November 12 (Box 66)
  - Minute books, 1832 March 16-1833 June 24 (Box 66)
  - Minute books, 1832 November 13-1837 March 30 (Box 67)
  - Minute books, 1837 March 31-1841 January 1 (Box 67)
  - Minute books, 1841 January 2-1845 November 22 (Box 68)
  - Minute books, 1845 November 26-1849 May 31 (Box 68)
  - Minute books, 1849 June 1-1852 January 15 (Box 68)
  - Minute books, 1861 April 23-June 19 (Box 68)